{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This man created a system of “burhs” for the defense of his kingdom, which eventually became known as “boroughs”. This man’s forces were attacked at Chippenham, which saw him retreat to Athelney. This man’s life was chronicled by Bishop Asser, and he converted the Danish king Guthrum to Christianity. For ten points, name this Anglo-Saxon king of Wessex in the 800s AD, the only English king to be given the epithet “the Great”.",
      "answer": "Alfred the Great or Alfred I"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Maori base their new year on the appearance of one star cluster in this constellation, to which the Parthenon is also oriented. In 1054, the first object cataloged by Messier appeared in this constellation, whose alpha star was named by Arabic astronomers for its following of the Pleiades. The Crab Nebula and Aldebaran are found in this constellation, which has been identified as Marduk, Nandi, and Io by various myth systems. For ten points, name this constellation, depicted by many ancient civilizations as a bull.",
      "answer": "Taurus"
    },
    {
      "question": "This author wrote “no more time’s dark events / charging like ceaseless clouds across the sky” in his elegy “Hush’d Be The Camps To-Day.” This man’s service as a volunteer nurse for the Union Army inspired the collection Drum-Taps, and he wrote an elegy in which “the great star early droop’d in the western sky”. For ten points, what poet eulogized Abraham Lincoln in “When Lilacs Last In The Dooryard Bloom’d” and “O Captain! My Captain!” from his collection Leaves of Grass.",
      "answer": "Walt Whitman or Walter Whitman"
    },
    {
      "question": "This leader ordered the genocidal Operation Anfal, carried out by Ali Hassan al-Majid; that operation included an attack on Halabja, where thousands of Kurdish people were killed by poison gas. This man was captured near Tikrit in a “spider hole” nine months after the U.S. invaded his country in 2003. For ten points, name this Ba’ath Party leader, the former dictator of Iraq.",
      "answer": "Saddam Hussein"
    },
    {
      "question": "The destruction of Port Dover was used as an excuse to attack this city, but a hurricane allowed the defending side to move back from Brookeville. Robert Ross led the military force that attacked this city, following his success at the Battle of Bladensburg. Paul Jennings recounted Dolley Madison’s efforts to save the portrait of George Washington from a burning building in this city. For ten points, name this city, burned by British troops near the end of the War of 1812.",
      "answer": [
        "Washington D.C.",
        "either"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man attempted to divest responsibility for causing a peasant war by writing Against the Murderous, Thieving Hordes of Peasants. He was sheltered by Frederick the Wise at Wartburg Castle, where he translated the New Testament into German. This man debated Ulrich Zwingli at the Marburg Colloquy and opposed the indulgences granted by men like Johann Tetzel. For ten points, name this father of the German Protestant Reformation.",
      "answer": "Martin Luther"
    },
    {
      "question": "This artist’s The Battle of the Kearsarge and the Alabama shows the Battle of Cherbourg during the American Civil War. This artist painted a nude woman looking toward the viewer while lounging next to a black cat and a black servant in Olympia. Raphael’s Judgement of Paris inspired this man’s painting of a nude woman who sits next to two fully clothed men at a picnic. For ten points, name this artist of Luncheon on the Grass.",
      "answer": "Edouard Manet"
    },
    {
      "question": "This event disrupted plans to create a utopian society known as New Helvetia. Newspaper owner Samuel Brannan heavily promoted this event, which led Levi Strauss to sell dry goods and denim overalls. This event was started after James Marshall made a discovery at Sutter’s Mill, and it led to the growth of San Francisco. For ten points, name this economic event in which “forty-niners” traveled to California.",
      "answer": "California Gold Rush"
    },
    {
      "question": "One construction in this city was covered with lapis lazuli and adorned with aurochs and dragons, symbolizing Adad and Marduk. Another construction in this city was legendarily built because Queen Amytis missed her Median homeland’s hills and greenery. For ten points, name this site of the Ishtar Gate, a Mesopotamian city where Nebuchadnezzar II built the Hanging Gardens.",
      "answer": "Babylon"
    },
    {
      "question": "The “imminent lawless action” test was formed after Clarence Brandenburg, a member of this group, sued the state of Ohio. The first leader of this organization was a general whose forces committed the Fort Pillow Massacre. A revival of this group at Stone Mountain took place after it was depicted suppressing voters in D. W. Griffith’s film Birth of a Nation. Nathan Bedford Forrest helped found, for ten points, what white supremacist organization?",
      "answer": "Ku Klux Klan"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country won the Battle of Hanko during a war where this country was led by Risto Ryi. Earlier this country was forced to give up the Karelian Isthmus that was protected by its unfinished Mannerheim line. This country fought the Continuation war with Nazi allies, but later turned on the Nazis in the Lapland war. For ten points, name this Scandinavian country that was invaded by the Soviets in the Winter War.",
        "answer": "Finland"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Finnish Army indirectly participated in the 872 day Nazi siege of this city that is currently called Saint Petersburg.",
        "answer": "Leningrad"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A cantata by this composer depicts a battle between the Teutonic Knights and the title Prince on the frozen Lake Peipus, and was based on his music for a Sergei Eisenstein film. This composer of Alexander Nevsky modeled his first symphony on the work of Haydn and wrote a work for children in which a bassoon depicts the title boy’s grandfather. For ten points, name this composer of the “Classical” Symphony and Peter and the Wolf.",
        "answer": "Sergei Sergeyevich Prokofiev"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Orchestras tune to a concert A played by what instrument, which represents the duck in Prokofiev’s Peter and the Wolf?",
        "answer": "oboe"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One of these people, Jean [ZHAHN] Calas, was unjustly accused of the murder of his son and was the subject of a work by Voltaire. These people were welcomed by Frederick William of Brandenburg in the Edict of Potsdam, and the Duke of Buckingham attempted to aid these people at the Siege of La Rochelle. One of their leaders, Gaspard de Coligny, was assassinated during an event targeting them, which occurred after the marriage of Marguerite and a king of Navarre. Henry IV led, for ten points, what religious dissidents in France, who were targeted in the St. Bartholomew’s Day Massacre?",
        "answer": "Huguenots"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Siege of the Huguenot stronghold of La Rochelle was led by what minister to Louis XIII, nicknamed the Red Eminence?",
        "answer": "Jean Armand du Plessis, Cardinal de Richelieu"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Max Weber pointed to double-entry bookkeeping as marking the beginning of notions of this concept, whose ratio to income was examined in a 2013 work by Thomas Piketty. That work about this concept “in the 21st century” dismisses its “human” type as a misnomer. Marx distinguished between its variable and constant forms in an uncompleted treatise he wrote about this concept. For ten points, name this economic concept that refers to the assets or wealth owned by a person, or to a good used in the production of other goods.",
        "answer": [
          "capital",
          "Capital in the 21st Century",
          "Das Kapital before mention"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Piketty is an author from this European country, where an economic school known as the Physiocrats believed that wealth was produced solely from land.",
        "answer": "France"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man, whose “treatment” intimidated opponents by moving uncomfortably close to them, was mentored by Speaker of the House Sam Rayburn. A close-up of a young girl’s eye cuts to a nuclear explosion in his controversial “Daisy” Ad. In a speech at the University of Michigan, this president outlined Head Start and Medicare as parts of his Great Society. For ten points, name this Texan who became president after John F. Kennedy was assassinated.",
        "answer": "Lyndon Baines Johnson or LBJ"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1968, Johnson bemoaned that he had “lost middle America” after this longtime CBS Evening News host spoke about the failures of the Vietnam War.",
        "answer": "Walter Cronkite"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "At a 2015 award ceremony, an actor impersonated this man threatening to kill Hannibal Buress. This man resigned from the board of Temple University, his alma mater, in 2014. In a 2005 deposition, this man admitted to illegally giving the sedative Quaalude to at least one woman. For ten points, name this actor and comedian who played Cliff Huxtable on a 1980s sitcom and has been accused by over 50 women of sexual assault.",
        "answer": "Bill Cosby"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This voice of Donkey in the Shrek films and former Saturday Night Live comedian did the aforementioned Bill Cosby impression while accepting the 2015 Mark Twain Prize for American Humor.",
        "answer": "Eddie Murphy"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Richard, the Earl of Cambridge, co-led the Southampton plot against this man. This man was wounded fighting Henry “Hotspur” Percy at the Battle of Shrewsbury, and this monarch, who signed the Treaty of Troyes during the Hundred Years War, led English forces to victory at the Battle of Agincourt. For ten points, name this Lancaster monarch who succeeded his father Henry IV, as king of England.",
        "answer": "Henry V"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Early in his youth Henry received military experience from fighting Owain Glyndwr, who was a prince of this region, whose current capital is Cardiff.",
        "answer": "Wales"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Robert J. Walker bribed Congressmen to approve of this action, which was negotiated by Eduard de Stoeckel. The Julian calendar was immediately replaced after this action, and Charles Sumner delivered a post-Civil War speech in favor of this action. Until the discovery of gold in the Klondike, this event was derided as “Seward’s Folly”. For ten points, name this $7.2 million purchase, roughly equal to 2 cents an acre, in which the U.S. acquired the future 49th state.",
        "answer": [
          "Purchase of Alaska",
          "equivalents"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Many landmarks in Alaska, including the strait separating it from Russia and the land bridge that once crossed it, are named for this Danish explorer who discovered some of the Aleutian islands.",
        "answer": [
          "Vitus Bering",
          "Bering Strait"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Louisiana",
      "prompt": "In Louisiana, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "most populous city, which was struck by Hurricane Katrina.",
          "answer": "New Orleans"
        },
        {
          "question": "President who signed the Louisiana Purchase.",
          "answer": "Thomas Jefferson"
        },
        {
          "question": "administrative districts that Louisiana uses in lieu of counties.",
          "answer": "parishes"
        },
        {
          "question": "city in Louisiana named for the “Hero of Two Worlds,” a French general who fought in the Revolutionary War.",
          "answer": [
            "Lafayette",
            "Marquis de Lafayette"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Governor, nicknamed the “Kingfish,” who was assassinated in 1935.",
          "answer": "Huey Pierce Long Jr."
        },
        {
          "question": "man who was arrested in 1892 for sitting in a train car that was for whites only?",
          "answer": "Homer Plessy"
        },
        {
          "question": "world’s longest bridge over water, which was controversially closed during Katrina?",
          "answer": [
            "Lake Pontchartrain Causeway",
            "any description of a bridge spanning Lake Pontchartrain"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "treaty that ceded control of Louisiana from Spain back to France in 1800.",
          "answer": "Third Treaty of San Ildefonso"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The British Royal Navy",
      "prompt": "Name...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "the appropriately-royal prefix to all of its ship names.",
          "answer": [
            "HMS",
            "Her and/or His Majesty’s Ship"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "the victory over Napoleon’s fleet in Egypt’s Aboukir Bay, near a famous river.",
          "answer": "Battle of the Nile"
        },
        {
          "question": "the admiral who died at, but won, the Battle of Trafalgar.",
          "answer": "Horatio Nelson"
        },
        {
          "question": "that admiral’s flagship at Trafalgar, the navy’s oldest commissioned vessel.",
          "answer": "HMS Victory"
        },
        {
          "question": "the all-big-gun ship that sparked an early 20th century arms race.",
          "answer": "HMS Dreadnought"
        },
        {
          "question": "the flagship of Force H, whose 1941 sinking sparked a hunt for the Bismarck.",
          "answer": "HMS Hood"
        },
        {
          "question": "the war where the Sheffield was sunk.",
          "answer": "Falklands War"
        },
        {
          "question": "the 1922 treaty that limited the size of the Royal Navy, as well as those of four other countries, eight years prior to a similar treaty signed in London.",
          "answer": "Washington Naval Treaty"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The New Year",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country that celebrates New Year with the dragon dance in cities like Beijing?",
          "answer": "People’s Republic of China"
        },
        {
          "question": "New York City intersection where a Waterford crystal ball is dropped on New Year’s Eve?",
          "answer": "Times Square"
        },
        {
          "question": "Roman god of doorways and gates celebrated on New Year’s, and for whom the first month of the western calendar is named?",
          "answer": "Janus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Robert Burns poem traditionally sung on New Year’s Eve?",
          "answer": "Auld Lang Syne"
        },
        {
          "question": "Jewish New Year holiday, on which the shofar is traditionally blown?",
          "answer": "Rosh Hashanah or Yom Teruah"
        },
        {
          "question": "Vietnamese New Year holiday, on which the North Vietnamese launched a surprise attack in 1968?",
          "answer": [
            "Tet Nguyen Dan",
            "Tet Offensive"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Calendar that began the New Year on 1 Vendemiaire [one ven-demi-air]?",
          "answer": [
            "French Republican Calendar",
            "French Revolutionary Calendar",
            "any description of the calendar instituted during the French Revolution",
            "the Paris Commune"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Pacific island country whose Line Islands are the first land west of the International Date Line?",
          "answer": [
            "Kiribati , but",
            "phonetic pronunciations"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A U.N. Secretary General from this country died in a 1961 plane crash en route to peace talks over conflict in the Congo Crisis. Another leader from this country was a prime minister (20 pts)",
        "assassinated in 1986 whose main suspect was Christer Pettersson. A king and military general from this nation died at the Battle of (10 pts)",
        "Lutzen and was known as the “Lion of the North”. For ten points, name this Scandinavian country whose leaders included Dag Hammarskjold, Olof Palme, and Gustavus Adolphus."
      ],
      "answer": "Sweden"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In a 1970’s memo, this company valued a human life at $200,000, justifying the non-installation of an $11 part that would prevent the rupture of fuel tanks in its (20 pts)",
        "Pinto model. This company produced the unpopular Edsel, named for the son of its founder, who built the River Rouge plant in Dearborn, (10 pts)",
        "Michigan and introduced the $5 daily wage. For ten points, name this American car manufacturer that introduced the Model T in 1908."
      ],
      "answer": "Ford Motor Company"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader, who with George Smythe co-founded the Young England group, was criticized by one politician about the Bulgarian Horrors in the (20 pts)",
        "Midlothian Campaign. This man represented the British delegation during the Congress of Berlin and used money from the Rothschild family to purchase shares for the Suez Canal. This leader gave the title Empress of (10 pts)",
        "India to Queen Victoria, who made him the First Earl of Beaconsfield. For ten points, name this 19th century Conservative Jewish Prime Minister who was the rival of William Gladstone."
      ],
      "answer": "Benjamin Disraeli"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Members of this religion prompted native Americans to attack members of the Baker- Fancher settlers in the (20 pts)",
        "Mountain Meadows Massacre. This religion’s founder wished to create a utopian “Zion” after being forced by Lilburn Boggs’s Extermination Order to migrate to (10 pts)",
        "Nauvoo, Illinois. For ten points, name this religion founded by Joseph Smith, whose members make up the majority of the population in Utah."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Mormonism",
        "Mormons",
        "Church of Jesus Christ of Latter Day Saints",
        "LDS"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One report on this event revealed communication between John Jastremski and Jim McNally; that report, a 243-page document written by Ted Wells, was limited by the destruction of a cell phone. A (20 pts)",
        "D’Qwell Jackson interception prompted this scandal, which ended with the forfeiting of a first round draft pick from (10 pts)",
        "Robert Kraft’s team but, ultimately, no suspension for Tom Brady. For ten points, name this 2015 scandal in which the New England Patriots were accused of tampering equipment during the NFL playoffs."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Deflategate",
        "Ballghazi",
        "any description of a scandal in which footballs were deflated"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After 100 days of exercise and incantations, members of this non-American movement believed they gained invulnerability to bullets. Members of this movement sieged the Legation Quarter until the (20 pts)",
        "Eight Nation Alliance freed them. This movement was supported until 1901 by the Dowager Empress (10 pts)",
        "Cixi [see-shee] of the Qing [ching] Dynasty in hopes of ridding China of foreigners. For ten points, name this nationalist movement, also known as the Society of Righteous and Harmonious Fists."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Boxers",
        "the Society of Righteous and Harmonious Fists until mentioned",
        "Boxer Rebellion and equivalents"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Bela Lyon Pratt created a statue of this man for his namesake fort in New Haven, Connecticut. Consider Tiffany wrote about the capture of this man in a tavern by Robert Rogers; this man was (20 pts)",
        "observing the movements of British troops after the Battle of Long Island. He was purported to say, “I only (10 pts)",
        "regret that I have but one life to lose for my country”. For ten points, name this American spy who was executed during the Revolutionary War."
      ],
      "answer": "Nathan Hale"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Winston Churchill proposed that this country be given Eastern Galicia, including the city of Lvov, in a “Plan B” regarding its proposed border. A line formed by two rivers and ending at (20 pts)",
        "Stettin now forms this country’s western border. The postwar Curzon and (10 pts)",
        "Oder-Neisse [NICE-uh] lines were drawn on either side of, for ten points, what European country which, on September 1, 1939, was invaded by Nazi troops to begin World War II?"
      ],
      "answer": "Poland"
    }
  ]
}